Leah: There are many source code
control solutions available today, and
it can become a little overwhelming
when deciding which one is appropriate.
Some are open source and have a large
supporting community of developers such as Git.
and others are more business centred,
focusing on larger teams and specific software
such as Microsoft Team Foundation Server.
Chris: Having the right system is important,
so there are key considerations that need to be
made when choosing a source control, such as:
• which programming languages it supports.
• the popularity – this is a consideration as
a popular solution such as Git has a large
community which could be useful if support
is needed, but also if a product is popular,
it is more likely to be kept up to date.
• Leah: is it fit for purpose – does it do
what it needs to do for a given project?
• what tools and features it includes – does
it have the necessary tools needed?
For example, does it have
a graphical user interface?
Or does it include a bug tracking system?
• Chris: ease of use – how
easy is it to learn and use?
Is it intuitive?
For example, GitHub is easier to
use than its counterpart Git, due
to its graphical user interface.
• hosting capabilities – is
it a cloud-based solution?
Is it open-source?
How much storage is available
for free and paid packages?
This is quite a serious consideration as
security and maintenance would also be a factor.
Some companies would choose to have their source
code solution on their own servers, but there are
also more modern Cloud solutions which will also
offer built in security such as Azure DevOps.
Leah: So, let’s have a look at some examples of
the more well-known source code control solutions.
GitHub is one of the most popular
online cloud-based hosting version
control which is owned by Microsoft.
It provides the distributed version control
of Git plus ‘access control’, ‘bug tracing’,
‘task management’, and ‘continuous integration’.
It provides a desktop application which
has a graphical user interface, within
which Git commands can be run without
using the command line, so therefore
simplifies the development workflow.
As a free version it can be used for personal
projects with smaller storage capacity,
but there is the option to upgrade to a
paid version which is more suitable for
companies with larger storage requirements.
It can manage multiple projects and
has good documentation and support.
Chris: Git is an open-source
distributed code control, that allows
version control for a repository.
It is good for intellectual software
applications, easy to learn and setup,
secure, and supports distributed versioning.
Leah: Bitbucket Server is good for teams already
using ‘Atlassian’ products such as ‘Jira’.
It suits team-based workspaces as well as
being a versioning solution, and it includes
project management, and collaboration.
Whilst benefitting by having an intuitive GUI,
and being easy to learn, integration with external
systems such as a CMS, can be rather tricky.
Chris: Team Foundation Server known as
Azure DevOps server is for teams that
use ‘Microsoft tools’ and is designed for
companies with its enterprise offerings.
It integrates easily with existing
Microsoft IDEs such as Visual
Studio and project management tools.
It can be expensive though and does
not have as much flexibility when
working with non-Microsoft tools.
Leah: Don’t forget to check out our
website links to find out more information!